Jessie A. and W. W. Charters Papers
Jessie A. and W. W. Charters Papers
1922-1953
Charters, Jessie Blount Allen, b. 1880
2 linear ft.
Jessie and W.W. (Werrett Wallace) Charters were pioneers in the field of adult education. Among other things, Jessie founded the Department of Adult Education at Ohio State University and W.W. was Director of Research at Stephens College in Colombia Missouri as well as the founding editor of the Journal of Higher Education. The collection includes correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, books and a manual, and primarily relates to Jessie Charters.
149429
Biographical History
Jessie A. and Werrett Wallace (W.W.) Charters were both pioneers in the field of adult education. Jessie Charters was born in Texas, September 23, 1880. Her family moved to Seattle, Washington in 1890. She obtained both a bachelor's (1899) and masters degree (1901) from the University of Washington. She received a PhD in Psychology in 1904 from the University of Chicago, where she studied philosophy under John Dewey and James R. Angell. Mrs. Charters was the first female on the west coast to receive a Ph D., and also to receive the highest honors ever for a woman. Jessie Charters was instrumental in the founding of Pi Lambda Theta educational fraternity. Dr. Charters held positions at Carnegie Institute of Technology, the University of Chicago and Ohio State University. Her primary area of interest was parental education and working with girls and women. Mrs. Charters died in 1971.
Werrett Wallace Charters was born October 24, 1875 in Hartford, Ontario. He received degrees from MacMaster (1896), Ontario Normal School (1899) and the University of Toronto (1901). In 1904 he received a PhD at the University of Chicago. Dr. Charters held positions at the University of Missouri, Carnegie Institute of Technology, the University of Pittsburgh, and the University of Illinois. He retired from Ohio State University in 1942 at age 66. Upon his retirement he became Director of Research at Stephens College in Colombia Missouri. Mr. Charters was the founding editor of the Journal of Higher Education. Mr. Charters' area of particular interest was the development of curriculum from nursery school through graduate level and professional development. Dr. Charters died March 8, 1952.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Material in the Jessie A. and W. W. Charters Papers covers the period 1922-1953, with the bulk of the material falling between 1922 and 1934. Material in the collection is arranged in alphabetical order by folder heading. Most of the material is related to Jessie Charters. Information related to W.W. Charters is indicated by his name on the folder.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
More information on Dr. Jessie Charters may be found in her papers housed at Ohio State University. Correspondence between W. W. Charters and his nephew, Alexander N. Charters will be found in the Alexander N. Charters Papers, housed at Syracuse University.
The bulk of W.W. Charters' papers are held by Ohio State University in their Rare Books and Manuscripts division.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Charters, Jessie Blount Allen, b. 1880.; Charters, W. W. (Werrett Wallace); Adult education -- Illinois -- Chicago.; Adult education -- Ohio.; Adult education -- United States.; Parenting -- Study and teaching.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuals (instructional materials); Photographs.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alexander N. Charters, nephew.
Inventory
- Papers
  - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Adult education, Ohio, 1928-1934 (Box 1)
  - Alumni education, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Chicago articles, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Chicago newspaper articles, 1928-1930 (Box 1)
  - Community activities, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Judge Baker Foundation Case Studies Series 1, 5-9, 14-19, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Leasure, Clara Lea, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Ohio State Conferences on Adult Education, 1929-1933; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ohio State University, Oct-Dec 1928 (Box 1)
  - Ohio State University, 1928-1932; 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Parent education scrap book, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Parents Laboratory Pre-School, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Parents study groups basic materials (Box 3)
  - Personal/biographical (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Jessie Charters (Box 3)
    - McCrimmon family (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - W.W. Charters (Box 3)
  - Publicity articles, 1930-1933 (Box 3)
  - School and society, April 2, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Tenth Avenue Baptist Church Sunday School Discussion Group, 1932-1934 (Box 4)
  - Training of children, 1930; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - W. W. Charters (Werrett Wallace)
    - Biographical information including genealogy (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Books
  - Charters, Jessie A. Young Adults and the Church. Abington Press, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Cutright, Prudence, W.W. Charters and Mae Knight Clark. Living Together in Town and Country. Macmillan Company, 1944 (Box 4)
  - "Educational Engineering: A Conference honoring Dr. Werritt Wallace Charters On the Occasion of his Retirement As Director of Research at Stephens College.", Oct. 17-18, 1949 (Box 4)
  - "Longfellow's Evangeline, Tales of a Wayside Inn, and Selections from Minor Poems.", 1890 (Box 4)
  - The World Review, 21 Sep - 23 Nov 1925 (Box 4)